Don Yoder collection of wire recordings
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Guides to the Collections in the Archive of Folk Culture
Don Yoder collection of wire recordings 1950-1960
AFC 1970/004
Yoder, Don
2 slips of paper + 26 sound wire reel containers.
sound recordings: 33 sound wire reels: analog; 3 in.
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.
Collection of field recordings of hymns and spirituals of Pennsylvania Dutch Evangelical United Brethren, United Christian, and Mennonite singers; humorous songs, secular folk songs, jokes, religious beliefs, tales, and conversations in Pennsylvania German; hymns, ballads, folk songs, tales, and ghost stories in English. Several interviews are about holidays, camp meetings, and traditional healing, including Sophia Bailer's discussion of Pennsylvania Dutch blessings for healing -- "brauche" -- also known as powwowing. Musical accompaniment includes guitar and fiddle for some recordings. One wire spool includes a radio broadcast from station WEEU of a program on "Pennsylvania Dutch folklore" presented by John B. Brendel.
Arrangement
Organized by format into the following series: 1. Manuscripts; 2. Sound Recordings.
Indexes
Recording logs prepared by Keith Reigart.
Acquisition
Don Yoder; loan for duplication, tape exchange; 1977.
William Woys Weaver; donation (12 wire reels); 2015.
Accruals
An accrual of 12 wires was received in 2015.
Additional Formats
Preservation tape reels: Washington, D.C.: Library of Congress Recording Laboratory, circa 1970. 4 sound tape reels: analog, 7 1/2 ips, mono.; 10 in. The sound recordings have been digitized from the preservation masters. Researchers can listen to the digital recordings in the Folklife Reading Room.
Related Material
Don Yoder collection of tape recordings (AFC 2003/051).
Access and Restrictions
Collection is open for research. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Additional Formats
Library of Congress duplication project, circa 1970. During duplication, some of the 32 wire reels originally acquired were found to be blank; the blank reels were deaccessioned. The remaining original wire recordings were retained by the American Folklife Center, Archive of Folk Culture.
Publications
Boyer, Walter E., Albert F. Buffington, and Don Yoder. Songs along the Mahantongo. Lancaster: Pennsylvania Dutch Folklore Center, 1951.
Yoder, Don. Pennsylvania Spirituals. Lancaster, Pennsylvania: Pennsylvania Folklife Society, 1961.
Biographical Notes
Born in 1921, in Altoona, Pennsylvania, Don Yoder grew up immersed in the traditions of Pennsylvania German culture. Educated at Franklin and Marshall College (A.B., 1942 and B.D., 1945), and at the University of Chicago (Ph.D., 1947). Yoder was chair of the Department of Folklore and Folklife at the University of Pennsylvania from 1966-1969, and retired from teaching after 40 years. He authored and co-authored hundreds of publications, traveled and lectured widely, and held varied posts, including director of the Pennsylvania Folklife Society (which he co-founded), editor of Pennsylvania Folklife, president of the American Folklore Society, and Professor Emeritus of Folklife Studies, University of Pennsylvania. He is a member of Phi Beta Kappa, and has been elected fellow to the American Antiquarian Society and the American Genealogical Society, among others. He introduced the European concept and practice of folklife studies in the United States. He died in 2015.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bailer, Sophia; Brendel, John B., 1911-1971; Yoder, Don
Organizations
Evangelical United Brethren Church.; Mennonite Brethren in Christ.; United Christian Church.; United Zion Church.; WEEU (Radio station: Reading, Pa.)
Subjects
Ballads, English--Pennsylvania.; Camp meetings--Pennsylvania.; Field recordings--Pennsylvania.; Folk songs, English--Pennsylvania.; Folk songs, Pennsylvania German--Pennsylvania.; Ghost stories--Pennsylvania.; Healing--Pennsylvania--Religious aspects.; Humorous songs--Pennsylvania.; Hymns, English--Pennsylvania.; Hymns, German--Pennsylvania.; Hymns, Pennsylvania German--Pennsylvania.; Mennonites--Pennsylvania--Hymns.; Pennsylvania Dutch--Pennsylvania--Folklore.; Pennsylvania Dutch--Pennsylvania--Music.; Pennsylvania Dutch--Pennsylvania--Religion.; Pennsylvania Dutch--Pennsylvania--Social life and customs.; Powwows (healers); Revival hymns--Pennsylvania.; Tales--Pennsylvania.
Form/Genre
Field recordings.; Interviews.; Jokes.; Prayers.; Radio programs.
Scope and Content
Collection of field recordings of hymns and spirituals of Pennsylvania Dutch Evangelical United Brethren, United Christian, and Mennonite singers; humorous songs, secular folk songs, jokes, hymns, religious beliefs, tales, and conversations in Pennsylvania German; hymns, ballads, folk songs, tales, and ghost stories in English. Several interviews are about holidays, camp meetings, and traditional healing, including Sophia Bailer's discussion of Pennsylvania Dutch blessings for healing -- "brauche" -- also known as powwowing. Musical accompaniment includes guitar and fiddle for some recordings. One wire spool includes a radio broadcast from station WEEU of a program on "Pennsylvania Dutch folklore" presented by John B. Brendel.
Recorded by Don Yoder and others at various locations in the Pennsylvania Dutch area of eastern Pennsylvania in 1950-1951, 1960, and possibly on other dates. Locations include Lancaster County, Lebanon County, Schuylkill County, Lehigh County, and Berks County, Pennsylvania.
Various performers and interviewees including Emma L. Yoder, Harry Lewis, Beulah Mae Lewis, Oliver Franklin Follweiler, Harvey Brunner Musselman, Miriam Hollenbach, Aggie Osman, Valeria Gable, Florence Gable, Florence Deibler, Martin Sweigert, Sophia Bailer, William (Willie) Brown, Christian R. Longenecker, Charles Fassnacht, Ella Fassnacht, Wesley Pfautz Martin, Mrs. Wesley P. Martin, and others.
Container List
- Series 1: Manuscripts
  - Documentation for sound recordings (original), 28 items: 26 containers and two slips of paper. (Box 1)
    26 original containers for wire reels and two pieces of paper. One paper accompanied AFC 1970/004: SR041 and one paper indicates the wires belong to Yoder. Further textual information on the containers and reels remains to be transcribed.
- Series 2: Sound Recordings
  - 1 sound wire reel (30 min., 44 sec.): analog, AFC 1970/004: SR11
    Recorded circa 1951-1960. 17 selections: folk songs and spoken word segments in Pennsylvania German and in English. The songs are sometimes sung a cappela, and sometimes accompanied by instruments. Several of the songs were published in the book Songs Along The Mahantongo. Recorded at the Pennsylvania Dutch Folklore Center (later the Pennsylvania Folklife Society).
  - 1 sound wire reel (15 min., 45 sec.): analog, AFC 1970/004: SR12
    Recorded July 13, 1960. 16 selections: spirituals in Pennsylvania German and in English. The songs are sung a cappela. Sporadic, brief talk can be heard between songs. Many of the songs are included with text and notation in Pennsylvania Spirituals.
  - 1 sound wire reel (part 1: 17 min., 11 sec.; part 2: 13 min., 47 sec.): analog, AFC 1970/004: SR13
    Recorded circa 1951-1960. 43 selections: hymns and songs in Pennsylvania German.
  - 1 sound wire reel (31 min., 16 sec.): analog, AFC 1970/004: SR14
    Recorded circa 1951-1960. 36 selections: songs in Pennsylvania German and in English. Nine hymns in Pennsylvania German are repeated from SR12.
  - 1 sound wire reel (19 min., 55 sec.): analog, AFC 1970/004: SR15
    Recorded circa 1951-1960. 24 selections: religious songs in Pennsylvania German, as well as spirituals in Pennsylvania German and in English. The first thirteen songs are repeated from SR14. The latter group of songs appear, with text and musical notation, in Pennsylvania Spirituals.
  - 1 sound wire reel (11 min., 20 sec.): analog, AFC 1970/004: SR16
    Recorded circa 1951-1960. 28 selections: fragments of spirituals sung in English by the same unidentified male singer, with no instrumental accompaniment.
  - 1 sound wire reel (22 min., 2 sec.): analog, AFC 1970/004: SR17
    Recorded July 13, 1960. 29 selections: spirituals in Pennsylvania German and in English. Only one selection is in English.
  - 1 sound wire reel (30 min., 56 sec.): analog, AFC 1970/004: SR18
    Recorded July 13, 1960. 28 selections: folks songs, spirituals, a counting rhyme, and a lullabye in Pennsylvania German. A prayer, possibly in Pennsylvania German, is sung. Also included are songs and ballads in English, and Pennsylvania German stories told in English.
  - 1 sound wire reel (12 min., 45 sec.): analog, AFC 1970/004: SR19
    Recorded July 13, 1960. 11 selections: folk songs and spoken word passages in English.
  - 1 sound wire reel (31 min., 24 sec.): analog, AFC 1970/004: SR20
    Recorded July 13, 1960. 12 selections: ballads and songs in English, and spoken word passages with some Pennsylvania German dialect mixed in. Sophia Bailer talks about powwowing.
  - 1 sound wire reel (17 min., 48 sec.): analog, AFC 1970/004: SR21
    Recorded July 13, 1960. 23 selections: spirituals in Pennsylvania German and a brief statement in English.
  - 1 sound wire reel (14 min., 32 sec.): analog, AFC 1970/004: SR22
    Recorded January 20, 1951. 20 selections: spirituals in Pennsylvania German and in English.
  - 1 sound wire reel (15 min., 59 sec.): analog, AFC 1970/004: SR23
    Recorded July 13, 1960. 27 selections: spirituals in Pennsylvania German.
  - 1 sound wire reel (14 min., 57 sec.): analog, AFC 1970/004: SR24
    Recorded July 13, 1960. 8 selections: includes spirituals in Pennsylvania German.
  - 1 sound wire reel (19 min.): analog, AFC 1970/004: SR25
    Recorded July 13, 1960. 61 selections: includes folk songs in German and Pennsylvania German, songs in Pennsylvania German, a story in Pennsylvania German and English, songs in English, and jokes in Pennsylvania German (with some English).
  - 1 sound wire reel (21 min., 5 sec.): analog, AFC 1970/004: SR26
    Recorded circa 1950. 37 selections: includes spirituals in Pennsylvania German and in English.
  - 1 sound wire reel (26 min., 13 sec.): analog, AFC 1970/004: SR27
    Recorded July 13, 1960. 32 selections: includes spirituals in Pennsylvania German and in English, and a Pennsylvania German-style German hymn.
  - 1 sound wire reel (15 min., 14 sec.): analog, AFC 1970/004: SR28
    Recorded July 13, 1960. 25 selections: includes folk songs, a lullabye, a joke, and a parody of a spiritual in Pennsylvania German; a humorous Pennsylvania German song in English; and a humorous song, folk songs, and a local prison ballad in English.
  - 1 sound wire reel (4 min., 9 sec.): analog, AFC 1970/004: SR29
    Recorded circa 1951-1960. 3 selections: includes two Pennsylvania German folk songs, and a conversation in English and Pennsylvania German between a male interviewer and a young girl.
  - 1 sound wire reel (23 min., 59 sec.): analog, AFC 1970/004: SR30
    Recorded circa 1951-1960. 28 selections: includes stories and folk songs in Pennsylvania German and other spoke-word segments, also in Pennsylvania German; also stories and an evangelical song (with a bawdy parody of the same song), and spoken-word segments in English.
  - 1 sound wire reel (14 min., 45 sec.): analog, AFC 1970/004: SR32
    Recorded circa 1952. 4 selections: includes three recordings of radio broadcasts, and a spoken word segment, all in Pennsylvania German. John Brendel was the host for at least two of the broadcasts.
  - 1 sound wire reel: analog, AFC 1970/004: SR33
    Transcribed from reel container: New Years wish – Jerome Fenstermaker
  - 1 sound wire reel: analog, AFC 1970/004: SR34
    Mr. MacG...le.
  - 1 sound wire reel: analog, AFC 1970/004: SR35
    Transcribed from reel container: Reinholds / Sup. with roanler [?] / Happy Hen.
  - 1 sound wire reel: analog, AFC 1970/004: SR36
    Recorded June 27, 1955. Transcribed from reel container: Miss Susan Balsbaugh.
  - 1 sound wire reel: analog, AFC 1970/004: SR37
    Transcribed from reel container: Peter Kershner / Transcribed by BBill Frey / DY [Don Yoder]: type words!!!.
  - 1 sound wire reel: analog, AFC 1970/004: SR38
    Recorded May 23, 1951. Transcribed from reel container and spool: Pete Kershner II / May 23, 1951 (Wednesday) / Transcribed July 25, 1955 / Nos. 10-30 / Orig.
  - 1 sound wire reel: analog, AFC 1970/004: SR39
    Recorded 1951. Transcribed from reel container and spool: Mrs. Jacob Sherk / [1951] [sic] / Bellgrove [sic] / Transcribed July 25, 1955 / Nos. 1-9 / Orig.
  - 1 sound wire reel: analog, AFC 1970/004: SR40
    Transcribed from reel container and spool: Geschimats [?] / Shoemakersville PA.
  - 1 sound wire reel: analog, AFC 1970/004: SR41
    Transcribed from reel container and spool: Rev. Mentzer / In the New Jerusalem / [other words, in Pennsylvania German].
  - 1 sound wire reel: analog, AFC 1970/004: SR42
    Transcribed from reel container and spool: Copy / 1) Emma Sherk 2) Pete Kershner / I.
  - 1 sound wire reel: analog, AFC 1970/004: SR43
    Transcribed from reel container and spool: Copy: 1) Pete Kershner 2) Susan Balsbaugh 3) Geo [George] Shaveley [?] / II.
  - 1 sound wire reel: analog, AFC 1970/004: SR44
    No available information.
- Appendix A: Logs and Notes for Sound Recordings